<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Notes from Jonathan McGlone</title>
 <link href="https://zeliangwang.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://zeliangwang.github.io/blog/"/>
 <updated>2020-08-14T22:59:10+01:00</updated>
 <id>https://zeliangwang.github.io/blog/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Zeliang Wang</name>
   <email>zeliang.w@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Using GitHub to Create and Host a Personal Website</title>
   <link href="https://zeliangwang.github.io/notes/2014/05/03/using-github-to-create-and-host-a-personal-website"/>
   <updated>2014-05-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://zeliangwang.github.io/blog/notes/2014/05/03/using-github-to-create-and-host-a-personal-website</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is an overdue note about my switch to using GitHub and Jekyll for this website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 10+ years using WordPress I finally made the switch to GitHub Pages (confession: I still use WordPress for certain projects at work). My switch largely centered around this rant that played itself out quite frequently in my head:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you want something simple, having a WordPress site often comes with a lot of other things: a web hosting plan, updating plugins, monitoring auto-updates so your site’s template and functionality don’t break, a MySQL database, dealing with being a target for hackers, a lot of clicking around and fussing with settings, hacking Thesis, and on and on. &lt;!-- flesh the previous sentence out with links --&gt; For a personal website that features just few pages, a CV, and maybe a place to write blog posts and link to your social media accounts and departmental web pages – or just experiment around with the awesomeness of HTML5 &lt;!-- flesh this out with links to codepen stuff or --&gt; and the amazing things you can do with client side scripting &lt;!-- ahem, more links --&gt;, WordPress is bloated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I really need to make a database call to serve an About page with less than 500 words on it? No. Do I want a bunch of third-party scripts from whatever plugin author(s) just to have social sharing tools? No. Do I want to have to hack PHP in an existing WordPress template to adjust the banner for my logo or to just simplify the user experience? No. I still want to be able to get up and running in less than five minutes, but can’t it be a little lighter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I made a wishlist of the things I wanted for a personal website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;simplicity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;good performance and reliability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no databases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hosting to be free or really cheap&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a custom domain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the ability to work on my site from anywhere if needed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to use open source tools supported by an active development community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to get up and running quickly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to have version control on my website, preferably Git&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to be able to share my code so others can easily re-use it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://staticgen.com/&quot;&gt;There are a lot of lightweight CMS options out there&lt;/a&gt;, but I fell for the GitHub + Jekyll toolchain. It’s well known and now pretty established, and the partnership it has developed with Jekyll developers (it’s based in Ruby) and its use of Markdown to separate content from markup just seemed to click with me as a digital publisher. It may not be for everybody, but after an afternoon playing around with and getting over the learning curve, I think it can be for a lot more than developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why after building my site from scratch (along with the help of Bootstrap), I’ve finally taken it a step further and created a &lt;a href=&quot;/guides/github-pages/&quot; title=&quot;Creating and Hosting a Personal Site on GitHub&quot;&gt;beginner’s guide to getting started building and hosting a personal website and blog with GitHub Pages and Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. It is very step-by-step. The goal is to make GitHub and Jekyll more accessible to a wider audience interested in an alternative to WordPress. It even refactors code to teach you how Jekyll templates work. And I should note, it was created to accompany a workshop I gave during &lt;a href=&quot;http://ttc.iss.lsa.umich.edu/ttc/enriching-scholarship/&quot;&gt;University of Michigan’s 2014 Enriching Scholarship Conference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Swatches. A Place to Think About Color on the Web</title>
   <link href="https://zeliangwang.github.io/notes/2013/12/12/swatches-a-place-to-think-about-color-on-the-web"/>
   <updated>2013-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://zeliangwang.github.io/blog/notes/2013/12/12/swatches-a-place-to-think-about-color-on-the-web</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Designers find inspiration and motivation from other designers. Everyday on the web we see things that are beautifully made by our peers – work that spark ideas for new projects or teaches us a new technique or technology. Recently, I’ve been trying to pay better attention to designers’ use of color on the web. I’m also working to combat my forgetfulness and feed my obsessive need to cata(log) aspects of my life in a really straightforward manner. While I’m already familiar with great services like Adobe Kuler’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://kuler.adobe.com/&quot;&gt;Wheel&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://kuler.adobe.com/explore/&quot;&gt;Explore&lt;/a&gt; tools and &lt;a href=&quot;http://colorschemedesigner.com/&quot;&gt;Color Scheme Designer&lt;/a&gt;, I’m interested in something much simpler, cleaner, and straightforward – HTML on a page with hex color values and ordered in reverse chronological order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter &lt;a href=&quot;https://zeliangwang.github.io/swatches&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Swatches&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a simple way to track sets of hex color values and also give attribution to those designers or sources that help me better understand color and how colors work together in design. Interested in how this works? &lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfiddle.net/jmcglone/hKXtF/&quot;&gt;See it at jsfiddle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In getting here, I’ve been heavily influenced by &lt;a href=&quot;http://dribbble.com&quot;&gt;dribbble’s&lt;/a&gt; design approach to color sets, as well as the attention it gives to color in the designs its users post and share in that space. But I’d like to be able to track sets of colors I find that work really well, as well as the hex color values that make up those sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, I’d like to develop a way to make this much more dynamic or work better with Jekyll but also a tool or service that others can utilize. In the meantime, I hope this is useful to people and inspires others to think more about color and using color on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Building Your Online Academic Identity</title>
   <link href="https://zeliangwang.github.io/notes/2013/10/08/building-your-online-academic-identity"/>
   <updated>2013-10-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>https://zeliangwang.github.io/blog/notes/2013/10/08/building-your-online-academic-identity</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I gave a workshop as a part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lsa.umich.edu/humanities/&quot;&gt;University of Michigan’s Institute for the Humanities&lt;/a&gt; Publishing Practice Series aimed at faculty and graduate students looking to build-up their online identity. There’s already been great work done by the writers at &lt;a href=&quot;http://chronicle.com/blogs/profhacker/creating-and-maintaining-a-professional-presence-online-a-roundup-and-reflection/43030&quot;&gt;ProfHacker&lt;/a&gt; on this topic, insightful tips over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.educause.edu/ero/article/intentional-web-presence-10-seo-strategies-every-academic-needs-know&quot;&gt;EDUCAUSE&lt;/a&gt;, and an article published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/3969/3292&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;First Monday&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; studying and classifying the types of online academic personas folks are starting to create for themselves. This workshop tried to bring all of that together and emphasize that building your online persona is really just SEO for your name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the previous folks were kind enough to share their thoughts with the world, I’ve kept that spirit and made my notes available – you can check them out at &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/Hn3Cc9&quot;&gt;http://goo.gl/Hn3Cc9&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
